Finding Aid for Netzorg family papers, late 1800s-2012.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Netzorg Family papers
late 1880s-2012
1938-1998
Netzorg family.
2012143 Aa 2
Papers of Morton Isadore and Katherine Smit Netzorg; their son Morton Jacob Netzorg and his wife Petra Fuld Netzorg; Petra Netzorg's mother Charlotte Fuld, and Petra's younger sister Bracha Fuld. The collection chronicles the history of the Philippine Islands in the 20th century, specifically during the Second World War; life of German Jewry on the eve of World War II; Zionist Insurgency in the British Mandate Palestine; developments in the scholarly field of South East Asian Studies and international publishing and book trade industries related to the region. The collection is a rich source of bibliographic material related to the Pacific Islands, primarily the Philippines, as well as the entire South East Asian region.
30 linear feet in 35 boxes, 1 oversize box, and 1 audio cassette box
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by David M. Netzorg (Donor No. 10682) on November 29, 2011. The original collection-title, in the Gift Agreement document, is: "The Papers of Morton Jacob ("Jock") Netzorg and Petra Fuld ("Pete") Netzorg, Husband and Wife."
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Morton I. Netzorg and Katherine S. Netzorg were both born in 1884. Morton was a Michigan native and a University of Michigan graduate (Literature, 1910). They came to the Philippines in 1911 to teach in the Philippine public schools as part of the Tomasites teacher corps. They had three children: Morton Jacob (born in 1912), called by most "Jock", David Leon, and Leah. Morton and Katherine soon became prominent and active members of the Manila Jewish community, public figures, and business owners. In the 1930s Morton I. worked on bringing European Jewish refugees to the Philippines as the Jewish Refugee Committee secretary. After the Japanese forces occupied Manila on January 2, 1942 Morton I. and Katherine were imprisoned in the Santo Tomas internment camp. They were liberated by the American forces in early February 1945. In April 1945 Morton became Regional Director of the Manila branch of the National Jewish Welfare Board and worked to organize community services and activities, and services for Jewish military personnel in the Philippines. In spring 1946 Morton I. Netzorg returned to the United States and died very suddenly shortly after his arrival. Katherine, who also returned, died in 1949. David L. Netzorg died of malaria in Japanese POW camp in 1942. Leah (married name Stine) resided in the United States.
Morton J. Netzorg arrived in the United States before the start of the War. There he met Hannelore "Floh" Fuld (born in 1923), a Jewish emigrant from Berlin, Germany. Hannelore subsequently changed her name to Petra and was known as Petra or Pete for the rest of her life. Morton J. and Petra were married in 1941 and had two children, Susan and David.
In the 1950s the Netzorgs settled in Detroit, Michigan and opened the Cellar Book Shop specializing in material published in and about the Southeast Asia region and the Philippines and the Pacific Islands in particular, as well as East and South Asia, and Africa. Their business became the essential source of material dedicated to these regions in North America. Morton acquired warehouses of books, maps and other Filipiniana material, and shipped them to Detroit. He built the largest collection of Philippine children's book and textbooks. Morton himself became one of the most important bibliographers of the Philippines. He published extensively in Kinaadman (Wisdom), journal published in the Philippines, and other scholarly journals, and authored a number of important Filipiniana bibliographies and bibliographical essays, notably about children's literature and about the World War II period in the Philippines, as well as memoirs.
Morton J. Netzorg died in 1995. Petra Fuld Netzorg continued running the Cellar Book Shop for a few years until her retirement. She died in 2008.
Petra's mother Charlotte "Lotte" Fuld and her younger sister Barbara "Bracha" (born in 1926) left Germany for England in 1938, then settled in the British Mandate Palestine in 1939. Petra's father Lothar Fuld stayed in Nazi Germany. He committed suicide after the pogroms of November 1938. As a teenager Bracha joined the Jewish Resistance movement against the British authorities in Palestine. She was killed in action during operation "Wingate Night" (March 27, 1946), when the Resistance units attempting to help illegal immigrants on the S.S. Wingate to land in Tel Aviv were attacked by British forces.
Lotte Fuld together with Petra and Morton established Bracha and Lotte Fuld Memorial Collection at the Jewish National and University Library in the late 1950s. Lotte resided in Israel then moved to California. Lotte Fuld died in 1968.
The Netzorg Family Papers are arranged into seven series: The Fuld Family Papers, Morton J. and Katherine S. Netzorg Papers, Morton J. and Petra Fuld Netzorg Papers, Visual Materials, Sound Recordings, Oversize Material, and Artifacts.
Family and business correspondence, including internment camp communications of Morton I. and Katherine; journals and diaries; published works and manuscripts of Morton J.; material related to Bracha Fuld's death; photographs; the Cellar Book Shop card catalog; also World War II-period artifacts, and Bracha's military ribbon.
Photographs and slides depicting Fuld and Netzorg families and their friends, Netzorgs' house in Detroit, Detroit street scenes, and the Cellar Book Shop. Of special interest are the World War II period photographs in the Morton I. and Katherine S. Netzorg part of the series depicting the conditions in liberated Philippines in 1945, military action and military life, and Jewish life in the U.S. military. Also of interest are the Fuld family photographs depicting Jewish life in Germany from the late 1800s to late 1930s. Slides with images taken during 1970s trips to the Philippines featuring Banaue, Cebu, Jolo, and Zamboanga, locations in the Southeast Asia, and Europe.
Recorded reminiscences of Morton J. Netzorg and Petra Fuld Netzorg.
Subjects:
Fuld family.; Fuld, Bracha, 1926-1946.; Netzorg family.; Netzorg, Katherine S.; Netzorg, Morton Isadore.; Netzorg, Morton J.; Netzorg, Petra Fuld.; Cellar Book Shop (Detroit, Mich.); National Jewish Welfare Board.; Santo Tomas Internment Camp (Manila, Philippines); Book industries and trade--Philippines.; Book industries and trade--Southeast Asia.; Book industries and trade--United States.; Booksellers and bookselling--Michigan--Detroit.; Jews--Germany--History--1933-1945.; Jews--Philippines--Manila--History--20th century.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; Palestine--History--1917-1948.; Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.; Philippines--History--Sources--Bibliography.; Southeast Asia--History--Sources--Bibliography.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fuld family.; Netzorg family.; Cellar Book Shop (Detroit, Mich.); National Jewish Welfare Board.; Bookstores.; Chaplains.; Clubhouses.; Soldiers.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines--Manila.; Detroit (Mich.); Germany.; Philippines.; Southeast Asia.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Fuld family.; Netzorg family.; Netzorg, Morton J.; Netzorg, Petra Fuld.; Germany--History--1918-1933.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.
Contributors:
Netzorg, Morton Isadore.; Netzorg, Morton J.; Netzorg, Katherine S.; Netzorg, Petra Fuld.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Slides.; Sound recordings.
- Fuld family papers
  The Fuld family papers series consists of correspondence between Lotte, Bracha, Petra, extended Fuld family members, and family friends. A large part of Fuld family correspondence is in German as the family gradually began to correspond in English in the mid-1940s. Correspondence contains letters sent from Germany in the late 1930s-early 1940s; letters by Lotte and Bracha sent from England and Palestine. Also in this series are Lotte's 1960s journals and some of her personal records and legal documents. Material related to Bracha's death and burial include letters sent to the family in March-April 1946; drafts of essays and articles about Bracha; Petra's reminiscences, clippings of newspaper articles in Hebrew and German; English translations of chapters from Bracha's biography by Sari Gal (Tel Aviv, 1999), and an English-language edition of The world's greatest women spies by Kurt Singer, that includes a chapter dedicated to Bracha. Also included is material about the Bracha and Lotte Fuld Memorial Collection at the Jewish National and University Library.
  - Correspondence
    - 1937-1959, 54 folders (Box 1)
    - 1960-1998 and, undated; 14 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous items, 1938 and; undated (Box 2)
  - Lotte Fuld materials
    - Journals, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Personal records, scattered (Box 2)
  - Bracha Fuld materials
    - Death and burial, 1946; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Biographical, 1982-2012; undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Bracha and Lote Fuld Memorial Collection at The Jewish National and University Library with gaps, 1953-2001; 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Allegiances, by Adelyn Bonin (Santa Barbara, Calif.: Fithian Press, 1993) (Box 2)
    - The world's greatest women spies by Kurt Singer (London: W.H. Allen, 1951) (Box 2)
- Morton I. and Katherine S. Netzorg papers
  The Morton I. and Katherine S. Netzorg series contains family records, such as copies of birth and death certificates, powers of attorney, forms of identification, and other legal documentation. Santo Tomas Internment Camp materials include internee messages sent through the Red Cross during Netzorgs' internment by the Japanese, hospital communications and memoranda, communications by Japanese authorities, ration cards, and camp ephemera. Correspondence includes family and non-family correspondence on various subjects, including personal and financial, as well as condolence letters sent to the family after Morton I. Netzorg's passing in 1946, and condolence letters sent to Morton J. (Jock) and Petra Netzorg after Katherine's passing in 1949. Morton I. and Katherine's writings and notebooks include essays, notes on various subjects of personal interest, recipes, and handwritten music. Financial records include accounts and cashbooks for the period between 1936 and 1945. War claims records include post-war family correspondence with authorities and lists of personal property, including lists of books in family library. Material on the subject of Jewish community of Manila includes correspondence with Jewish relief organizations. Also included is material related to death and burial of David L. Netzorg, Jock's brother, who died of malaria while in internment in Camp O'Donnell in 1942. Among printed material is a photocopy of the 1925 edition of "Better English for speaking and writing for grades six and seven" by Carlos P. Romulo, Katherine S. Netzorg, and Sarah E. Simons (Philadelphia, Toronto, Manila: John C. Winston Co.) and the Pennsylvania Railroad reprints of fiction for the military and a self-published brochure.
  - Netzorg family records
    - Morton I. Netzorg (Box 2)
    - Katherine S. Netzorg (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Family, 1940-1941; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Santo Tomas Internment Camp, 1942-1945; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Post-liberation correspondence
      - Family, 1945-1947; 6 folders (Box 3)
      - Non-family, 1945-1946; 7 folders (Box 3)
      - Katherine Netzorg’s correspondence, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Condolence letters, Morton I. Netzorg, 1946 (Box 3)
    - Condolence letters, Katherine S. Netzorg, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Writings by Morton I. Netzorg
    - Various, 1928 (Box 3)
    - Morton in the Mountains, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Notebooks, 1944-1945 and; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - David L. Netzorg, 1946-1949 (Box 3)
  - Financial records, 1934-1946; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - War claims records, 1946-1953; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Jewish community of Manila, 1945-1947 (Box 3)
  - Better English for speaking and writing for grades six and seven by Carlos P. Romulo, Katherine S. Netzorg, et al., 1925 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, 1942-1943; undated (Box 3)
- Morton J. and Petra Fuld Netzorg papers
  The Morton J. and Petra Fuld Netzorg papers series is the largest in the collection and contains personal and family papers; Morton's writings and publications, correspondence, materials related to the extended Netzorg family; Petra's files include her correspondence, journals, and writings.
  The Family papers subseries contains Netzorg family genealogy files, family newsletters and annual letters.
  - Morton J. Netzorg files
    - Biographical material
      - Interviews, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Jock Netzorg: Manila memories, by Michael P. Onorato, 1988 (Box 4)
      - Manila Central-Bordner School reunions, 1980-1989 (Box 4)
      - Morton J. Netzorg Festschrift, 1989 (Box 4)
      - My friend Jock, by Petra F. Netzorg (draft), 1995 (Box 4)
      - Reminiscences by family friends, 1986-1988 (Box 4)
      - View from the Pasiq, by Morton J. Netzorg, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Writings
      - Background of experimental roughing, undated (Box 4)
      - Bibliographical control (proposal, undated) (Box 4)
      - Books for children in the Philippines, 1982; undated; 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Filipiniana: 1969 and draft, 1969 (Box 4)
      - Filipiniana bibliographies in the 20th century, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Filipino childhood, mainly as seen in schoolbooks draft, undated (Box 4)
      - In Spain they say, undated; 2 volumes (Box 4)
      - Jack Horner in the Philippines, 1978 (Box 4)
      - Kinaadman articles with gaps, 1979-1985; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Leyte Samar bibliography, 1977 (Box 5)
      - MacMicking correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 5)
      - Mystery floating islands, 1980 (Box 5)
      - NEH grant applications, 1980 (Box 5)
      - Operations research: the basics, by E. Leonard Arnoff and Morton J. Netzorg, 1965 (Box 5)
      - Philippine bibliography and related correspondence, 1978 (Box 5)
      - Philippine ethnic literature, undated (Box 5)
      - Philippine Quarterly of Culture & Society articles, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
      - Philippine-American interactions revealed in fiction for children about World War II, undated (Box 5)
      - Philippines in mass market novels, 1988 (Box 5)
      - Philippines in World War II and until independence (related correspondence), 1970-1978 (Box 5)
      - To see such sport, undated (Box 5)
      - Two ships and two lighters (1930s), 1985 (Box 5)
      - Universal voyager (translation, undated) (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1980s-1990s (Box 5)
    - Lectures, undated (Box 5)
    - Consulting work, 1975-1979 (Box 5)
  - Petra Fuld Netzorg files
    - Correspondence
      - With gaps, 1968-2005; 10 folders (Box 5)
      - 2006, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Trips
      - Europe and Asia, 1958; 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Philippines and Vietnam, 1969 (Box 6)
      - Philippines, 1975-1976 (Box 6)
      - Philippines, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
    - Journals 1938-1981 with gaps and undated (Box 6)
    - Memory Book interviews transcripts, 1994; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Writings, 1939; 1971 and; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1961-1968 (Box 6)
  - Family files
    - Genealogy (Box 7)
    - Never a dull moment, 1949-2000; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Scrapbooks See also Oversize, 1957-1987; 8 folders; 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Netzorg family newsletters, 1949-2001; 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    Netzorgs' correspondence constitutes the largest part of the series. It contains correspondence between Morton J. and Petra, as well as their correspondence with family members, friends, business partners, customers, and various organizations and institutions; annual newsletters from friends and family in the United States, the Philippines, and from around the world; as well as material related to Morton J. and Petra's business travel. The Correspondence subseries is organized in alphabetical order by name of correspondent or organization, with the exception of a small segment for select years. Morton and Petra tended to separate personal from business in their correspondence with friends who were also customers, but filed both types of letters together.
    Most of the business correspondence relates to scholarly subjects and publishing in the field of Southeast Asian and Pacific studies, rare books and periodicals, and inquiries. Netzorgs' business correspondence is a rich source of bibliographic information and complements material located in the Cellar Book Shop series described below.
    Over the years the Netzorgs have exchanged letters with a number of important scholars, writers, and artists, as well as American and foreign politicians and diplomats, religious leaders, educators, and entrepreneurs. The series includes correspondence with Lydia (Lyd) Arguilla (1914-1969), noted Filipino artist, and her sister Remedios Piñon; Tita Ayala (b. 1931), Philippine writer, poet and multi-media artist; Father Miguel A. Bernad (1917-2009), Filipino Jesuit priest, scholar, author, and editor of several Philippine academic journals; Charles T. R. Bohannan (1914-1982) U.S. counter-guerilla expert who advised the Philippine military forces, and took part in U.S. military operations in South Vietnam and Cuba; Filipino American historical and political fiction writer Linda Ty Casper (b. 1931); author Bernard Covit (1907-1978) who was prisoner in Manila civilian internment camp with Morton I. and Katherine Netzorg; leader of the Thirteen Moderns art movement Filipino painter Victorio C. Edades (1895-1995) and his wife Jean Edades (b. 1907), founder of the Philippine Theatre Davao; Randall Gould (1898-1979), Shanghai Evening Post and Mercury editor and publisher between 1931 and 1949; Congresswoman Martha W. Griffiths (1912-2003), a key figure in bringing women's rights legislation to successful passage in Congress; author and The New Yorker writer Emily Hahn (1905-1997); James J. Halsema (1919-2005), Philippine scholar, war correspondent, Japanese internment camp prisoner, and US Foreign Service officer; Lt. Col. Ray C. Hunt (b. 1919), writer and survivor of the Bataan Death March who fought among Filipino guerilla forces against the Japanese Imperial Army; Thelma James (1899-1988), Detroit teacher, collector, and archivist of urban folk traditions; military and diplomatic history scholar Ricardo T. Jose (b. 1957); Rolf M. Kneller, Israeli photographer who headed a team of camera operators during the Adolf Eichmann trial in 1961; Oscar Lopez, who corresponded with the Netzorgs on behalf of his father, Eugenio Lopez, Sr. (1901-1975), owner of the Manila Chronicle and founder of the Philippine Chronicle Broadcasting Network; Salvador P. Lopez (1911-1993), Ilokano writer and journalist, Philippine's Secretary of Foreign Affairs and diplomat, and president of the University of the Philippines; a small exchange of letters with President of the Philippines Ramon Magsaysay (1907-1957); founder and first president of the Philippine Writers' League Federico Mangahas (1904-1979); Maung Maung (1925-1994), Supreme Court Chief Justice and civilian president of Burma (Myanmar) in August-September 1988; Henry (Hank) Miller (1919-1985), U.S. Information Agency officer and creator of Southeast Asian and African regional programs centers for the Voice of America; Colonel John E. Olson (b. 1917), survivor of the Bataan Death March; Yay Panlilio (1913-1978), journalist and leader in Philippine resistance against the Japanese; Carlos L. Quirino (1910-1999), Filipino historian and writer, and Bataan survivor; noted scholar and Detroit native William Henry Scott (1921-1993); Alma G. Stallworth (b. 1932), Michigan state legislator and founder of the Black Caucus Foundation in Michigan; Romeo V. Tabuena (b. 1921), Philippines-born painter and printmaker; Admiral Kemp Tolley (1908-2000), U.S. Navy historian; Manuel A. Viray, Philippine diplomat and author; American writer Erich V. Von Neff; abstract painter Fernando Zóbel (b. 1924); among many other noted individuals, as well as companies, businesses and organizations.
    - Between Morton J. and Petra Netzorg
      - With gaps, 1941-1958; 6 folders (Box 7)
      - 1959-1988, 9 folders (Box 8)
    - Abaya, Antonio, 1966-1983 (Box 8)
    - Abendroth, William, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Abraham, Abie, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Abrahams, Roger, 1962-1963 (Box 8)
    - Adamany, Hank, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Adams, Florence with gaps, 1946-1973; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Adams, Glen scattered, 1970-1988 (Box 8)
    - Adams, Richard and Roberta, 1950-1957 (with gaps) (Box 8)
    - Adamson, Sofia, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Advincula, Frederick, 1940-1942 (Box 8)
    - Afable, Patricia, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
    - African Studies Association, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Agahan, Pablo, 1968-1975 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Agoncillo, Teodoro, 1957-1962 (Box 8)
    - Ahern, Sheila and Brian, 1967; 1983 (Box 8)
    - Akamatsu, Muriel, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Alabado, Ceres, 1969-1981 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Aldine Publishing Co., 1966; 1968 (Box 8)
    - Alemar’s, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Alexander, Joseph and Wilma, 1953; undated (Box 8)
    - Altrusa Club of Detroit, 1965; 1975 (Box 8)
    - Alzona, Emanción, 1956-1957 (Box 8)
    - Amador, Stephen, 1977 (Box 8)
    - American Association of the Philippines, 1973-1997 (with gaps) (Box 8)
    - American Committee on the History of World War II, 1979 (Box 8)
    - American Defenders of Bataan and Corregidor, 1957-1983 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - American Ex-Prisoners of War, Bataan Chapter, 1975; 1985-1986 (Box 8)
    - American Historical Committee, 1972; 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - American Statistical Association, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
    - Ananda, Peter, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Anderson, Gerald, 1963-2002 (with gaps) (Box 8)
    - Anderson, John (campaign), 1981; 1983 (Box 8)
    - Andjulis, Eileen, 1987-1991 (Box 8)
    - Ando, Hirofumi, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
    - Ang, Gertrude, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Angeles, Linda Maria N., 1973-1976 (with gaps) (Box 8)
    - Angliongto, Jose, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Ankenbrand, Kate, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Anonas family, 1976-1977 (Box 8)
    - Antioch College, 1961-1962; 1972 (Box 8)
    - Antonio, Robert, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Araneta, Salvador, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Archer, Eric H., 1986-1987 (Box 8)
    - Arguilla, Lydia, 1940-1970; undated; 11 folders (Box 8)
    - Armstrong, Charles, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Arnaldo, Solomon, 1954; 1956 (Box 9)
    - Arnoff, E. Leonard and Ann, 1958-1985 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Arpon, Winston, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Asia Society, New York, 1962; 1966 (Box 9)
    - Asian Perspectives, 1961-1966 (Box 9)
    - Ateneo de Manila, 1963-1975 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Auerbach, Jack, 1962-1977 (scattered) (Box 9)
    - Avner, Henny, 1962-1979 (with gaps) (Box 9)
    - Ayala, Tita, 1984-1986 (Box 9)
    - Azikiwe, Nnamdi (office), 1963-1966 (Box 9)
    - Babcock, Mary J. and William, 1960-1970 (with gaps) (Box 9)
    - Bagley, Gary and Trudy, 1979-1983 (with gaps) (Box 9)
    - Bailey, Peter, 1944; 1984; undated (Box 9)
    - Baird, Robert, 1999-2002 (Box 9)
    - Baker, John, 1983; undated (Box 9)
    - Balaba family, 1975-1984; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Banyai, Richard, 1973-1975; 1985 (Box 9)
    - Baradi, Edita, 1978; 1981 (Box 9)
    - Barrios, Antonio, 1986 (Box 9)
    - Bartolabac, Dominador, 1976; 1984 (Box 9)
    - Bartsch, William, 1978-1988 (with gaps) (Box 9)
    - Barua, Birichi K., 1963 (Box 9)
    - Basch, Lili, 1947-1948; 1959 (Box 9)
    - Basinger, Jo and Willia, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Bataan Relief Organization of Detroit, 1944-1945 (Box 9)
    - Baumgardner, G. G., 1965 (Box 9)